Welcome everybody.
환영합니다, 여러분
So in the past I've said quite a few times, I am excited to start this this week or this topic.
과거에도 몇 번 말씀드렸는데요 이번 주 혹은 이번 주제를 시작하게 되어 정말 신나요
And I want to say that all of that has been nonsense, because the excitement that I've had has paled
그 모든 게 말도 안 된다고 말씀드리고 싶어요 제가 느꼈던 흥분은 오늘 느끼는
in significance compared to the level of excitement I have today.
흥분에 비하면 아무것도 아니었거든요
As we start week six and we embark upon the world of training, this is what it's all about.
6주 차를 맞아 세계 훈련에 돌입합니다 바로 이거죠
Now it gets real.
이제 실감이 나네요
Prepare yourself.
준비하세요
So up to this point, we've always been talking about what they call inference.
지금까지 우린 추론이라는 걸 늘 얘기했죠
And inference is when you take a model that's been trained to against a ton of data, and it's then
추론은 엄청난 양의 데이터에 대항하도록 훈련된 모델을 런타임에 사용하여
used at runtime to predict the next token given an input.
입력을 받은 다음 토큰을 예측하는 거예요
And we've been looking at different ways to get that inference better and better.
그 추론을 더 좋게 하려고 다양한 방법을 찾고 있어요 Get it
We're now going to go and look at the models themselves and understand how can you train models so that
이제 모델 자체를 살펴보고 모델을 어떻게 훈련할 수 있는지 알아보죠
they are even better at runtime and inference.
런타임과 추론에서 더 잘하도록요
And this this is where it gets advanced.
여기서부터 발전하는 거죠
We start with the less glamorous part of it, which is about the data.
덜 화려한 부분부터 시작하죠 데이터에 관한 거예요
And whilst crafting a data set might might not sound as glamorous, it isn't as glamorous.
데이터 세트를 만드는 게 그렇게 멋져 보이지 않을지 몰라도 실제로도 그래요
It happens to be absolutely essential and perhaps one of the most important parts.
절대적으로 필수적이고 가장 중요한 부분 중 하나죠
And we're going to spend today and tomorrow spending, getting really deep into the data, understanding
오늘과 내일 우리는 소비를 하며 데이터에 깊이 파고들고 처음부터 끝까지 이해하고
it back to front, visualizing it, cleaning it up, curating it, getting it to a form where we really
시각화하고, 정돈하고, 큐레이팅해서 우리가 정말 좋아하는 형태로
like it a lot.
만들 거예요
Um, and that's something that you have to do.
그렇게 해야만 하죠
We're also going to spend some time understanding, how are we going to gauge success of this project?
또한 시간을 들여 이해하려고 합니다 이 프로젝트의 성공을 어떻게 가늠할까요?
What are we trying to achieve and how do we know if we've done it or not?
우리는 무엇을 이루고 싶으며 성공했는지 어떻게 알 수 있을까요?
But first, let's talk for a second about the eight weeks that you've had, where you've come from and
하지만 먼저 8주 동안의 경험에 대해 얘기해 보죠 어디서부터 어떻게 시작했는지 앞으로 어떻게
where you are going.
될지에 대해서요
We started some time ago now, six weeks ago, uh, right on the left where you're heading is an LM
6주 전에 시작했어요 왼쪽을 보시면 달 착륙선 엔지니어링 마스터가
engineering master.
있어요
Over on the right.
오른쪽에 있어요
In week one, we talked about frontier models, and we tried some of them out.
1주 차에는 개척자 모델에 대해 얘기했고 몇 가지를 시도해 봤어요
In week two we were using multiple APIs.
2주차에는 다중 API를 사용했죠
We were building UIs with Gradio and Multi-modality.
그래디오와 다중 모듈로 UI를 구축했어요
Week three we explored hugging Face the Pipelines Tokenizers and then the models.
3주 차에는 페이스 더 파이프라인 토큰이저와 모델을 살펴봤죠
In week four, we were selecting models.
4주 차에 모델들을 선발했어요
We were using code generation and we built something that was what, 60,000 times faster?
코드 생성을 사용했고 60,000배 빠른 걸 만들었죠?
It was able to optimize code 60,000 times is remarkable.
코드를 60,000배 최적화할 수 있었다는 건 놀라워요
Week five.
5주 차예요
Last week, of course, was rag all about rag very hot topic.
지난주에는 래그에 관한 래그의 뜨거운 토픽이었죠
And now that brings us to week six fine tuning a frontier model where we've arrived at training in week
이제 6주 차로 접어들었어요 개척지 모델을 세밀하게 조정했고 7주 차에는 훈련을 시작했어요
seven.
다음에 또 해요
But now.
지금은요
Now we'll be dealing with open source models and basically building our own model.
오픈 소스 모델을 다룰 겁니다 기본적으로 우리 고유의 모델을 구축하는 거죠
And week eight is where it all comes together.
8주 차부터 모든 게 합쳐지죠
So with that, let's talk a bit about the transition that we are now making.
이제 비트를 가지고 우리가 만들고 있는 변화에 대해 얘기해보죠
We are moving from inference to training as I say.
추론에서 훈련으로 전환하고 있어요
So let's just talk about when we when we've been working on inference, what have we been doing.
추론을 작업했을 때 얘길 해보죠 뭘 하고 있었죠?
We've we've developed different techniques so that when we are running these models, we can try and
다양한 기술을 개발해서 이 모델들을 실행할 때 성능을 더 향상하려고
get them to perform better and better.
노력해요 get it
We've tried Multi-shot prompting when we give it lots of examples for it to work on.
작업 예시를 많이 주면서 멀티샷 프롬프트도 해봤어요
We've tried prompt chaining when we send multiple different messages and build on top of each other
여러 개의 다른 메시지를 보내고 빌드를 해서 결과를 조합하는 프롬프트 연결을
and combine the results.
시도했었죠
We've used tools where we had the model almost be able to call back into our code, although it wasn't
모델을 코드로 불러올 수 있는 도구를 사용하기도 했어요 그렇게 마법 같지는
quite that magical.
않았지만요
In order to do things like calculate the price of an airline ticket or the price of to travel to a different
항공권의 가격을 계산하거나 다른 도시로 가는 여행 비용을 계산하는
city.
거죠
And then most recently, we worked on Rag injecting more relevant content context into the prompt.
가장 최근에는 Rag 인젝팅에 대해 작업했습니다 더 관련 있는 콘텐츠 컨텍스트를 프롬프트에요
So all of these, what they have in common is they're all about taking an existing trained model and
이 모든 것의 공통점은 현존하는 훈련 모델을 취해 그것이 아는 것을 최대한 활용하기
figuring out how we can best use it to take advantage of what it knows by calling it multiple times,
위해 어떻게 이용할지 알아내는 거죠 여러 번 호출하고 컨텍스트에 추가하는
adding in context, and so on.
식으로요
What we're going to do now is move on to training.
이제 훈련으로 넘어갈 거예요
So in training, what we're trying to do is take a deep neural network, potentially with its billions
그래서 훈련 때 수십억 개의 매개 변수가 있는 신경망을 활용해 그 매개
of parameters, and figure out how can we tweak those parameters, change those weights, optimize them
변수를 수정하고 무게를 변경하고 데이터에 근거해 최적화할 방법을
very slightly based on data so that it gets better and better at predicting future tokens, and whilst
연구합니다 그러면 미래 토큰을 예측하는 게 더 쉬워지죠 추론하기 위해 더 많은 컨텍스트를 추가하는
adding in more context at inference and things like that is a is a bit of a broad brush stroke in terms
등 다양한 방법을 연구합니다 결과에 영향을 주는 측면에서 보면 일종의 붓
of how you can affect the outcomes with training.
터치로군요
It's a much more nuanced technique that allows you to gradually build up deeper, finer grained understanding
훨씬 미묘한 기술로 점점 더 깊고 섬세한 결로 문제를 이해할 수
of the problem you're trying to solve.
있게 해주죠
Now, trying to train a multi-billion parameter LLM is a rather expensive proposition.
LLM을 수십억 매개 변수로 훈련하는 건 꽤 비싼 제안이죠
It's something that the Frontier Labs probably spend well, they do spend north of $100 million on training
프런티어 연구소들은 아마 1억 달러 이상을 최고의 모델을 훈련하는
their their best models, and that's outside my budget.
데 쓸 텐데 제 예산 밖이에요
And I'm guessing it's outside your budget.
예산도 안 맞겠죠?
And so that's unfortunately not possible for us.
불행히도 그건 불가능하죠
But luckily we could take advantage of something called transfer learning.
다행히도 전송 학습이라는 걸 이용할 수 있었죠
And transfer learning says that it's perfectly doable to take an existing trained LM, a model that's
트랜스퍼 러닝에 따르면 훈련된 기존 LM을 취하는 게 완벽하게 가능합니다 엄청난 양의
already been pre-trained on a ton of data, and you can then just continue the training with a particular
데이터로 이미 훈련된 모델이죠 그런 다음 특정 데이터 집합으로 훈련을 계속할 수 있어요
Perhaps that solves a very specialized problem, and it will sort of transfer all of the knowledge that's
아마도 아주 전문적인 문제를 해결하고 이미 축적된 모든 지식을
already accumulated, and you'll be able to add on some extra knowledge on top of that.
이동시켜 그 위에 추가된 지식을 추가할 수 있겠죠
Um, and so you could take a pre-trained model space and then you can sort of, um, you can, you can
미리 훈련된 모델을 가지고 작업에 더 정밀하게
make it more precisely trained for your task.
훈련할 수 있어요
And that process is known as fine tuning.
그 과정을 미세 조정이라고 하죠
Um, as just, just as it sounds.
말 그대로예요
Um, and of course, we're going to be using some techniques that I've name dropped in the past, like
물론 몇 가지 기술을 사용할 거예요 제가 전에 언급한 적이 있죠
Q Laura, as ways to do it.
큐 로라 같은 방법으로요
That will be manageable in terms of memory and so on.
메모리 같은 측면에서 관리할 수 있어요
So let me now introduce the the problem, the commercial problem that we are going to be working on
이제 문제를 알려 드리죠 앞으로 몇 주 동안 우리가 씨름할
for most of the next few weeks.
상업적 문제요
So let's say we work at an e-commerce company or a marketplace company working in products, and we
전자 상거래 회사나 마켓플레이스 회사에서 제품을 만든다고 해보죠 거의 모든 제품에
want to build a model that can take a description of any of almost any product, a wide variety of products,
대한 설명을 담을 수 있는 모델을 구축하고자 합니다 다양한 제품들
let's say electrical electronic products or computers, fridges, washing machines and other things
예를 들어 전자 제품이나 컴퓨터, 냉장고, 세탁기 같은 가정과 차에 사용하는
for the home and car and be able to estimate how much it costs based just on the description.
제품들 말이죠 그리고 설명을 바탕으로 가격을 추정할 수 있어야 하죠
Um, now, uh, that's it's a it's a nice, easy to understand problem.
그건 쉽고 이해하기 쉬운 문제예요
It's got a very easy to measure outcome.
결과를 측정하기 아주 쉬워요
You might if the data scientists amongst you might raise your hand and say, that doesn't particularly
여러분 중 데이터 과학자가 손을 들고 텍스트를 생성하는 인공지능
sound like a problem that's designed for a generative AI solution that generates text.
용액을 위해 설계된 문제 같지 않다고 말할 수도 있죠
Sounds like something that needs a model that creates a number.
숫자를 만드는 모델이 필요한 것 같네요
And typically that's the domain of what people call regression models.
이게 회귀 모델의 도메인이죠
Types of models that produce a number that you can then try and fit to, um.
모델의 종류에 따라 숫자를 만들어 거기에 맞추는 거죠
And you'd be right.
당신 말이 맞아요
You'd be making a valid point.
당신 말도 일리가 있어요
It is typically more a regression kind of problem.
보통 퇴행하는 것에 더 가깝죠
Um, but it turns out it's still is going to be a great problem for us to work with.
하지만 여전히 우리가 다루기엔 큰 문제인 것 같아요
And there's a few reasons for that.
거기엔 몇 가지 이유가 있어요
One of them is that turns out frontier models are actually great at solving this kind of problem to
그 중 하나는 개척자 모델이 이런 문제를 해결하는 데 좋다는 겁니다 텍스트를
to start with, they were intended just to generate text and just to be able to do things that involve
생성하는 데만 사용되며 요약이나 다른 텍스트 생성
things like tasks like summarization and other and other text generation activities.
활동과 관련된 작업을 하는 데 사용되죠
But as we've discovered, when we ask a model to respond in JSON and respond with with information,
하지만 모델에 JSON 내에서 반응하도록 요청하고 정보로 반응하게
it can be very effective at responding back with quantitative results.
하면 양적 결과로 대응하는 데 아주 효과적일 수 있어요
And so actually the frontier models, um, perhaps because of the emergent intelligence we talked about
개척 모델은 아마도 우리가 오래전에 얘기했던 신생 지능
a long time ago, now have become highly effective at even these kinds of problems that were traditionally
덕분에 퇴행 모델이라는 영역에서 특히 효과적인 문제를 해결할
the domain of a regression model.
수 있게 된 거죠
So it is absolutely possible to use JNI for this.
JNI를 사용할 수 있어요
And in fact, you'll see the frontier models are going to do spectacularly well at this better than
프런티어 모델도 성능이 뛰어납니다. 우리가 만들 단순 회귀
simple regression models that we'll build to.
모델보다 훨씬 낫죠.
So it turns out that it does work in this space.
이 공간에서 작동하는 게 밝혀졌어요
Um, it's also going to be much more enjoyable for us when we try and build our own models.
우리만의 모델을 만들 때 훨씬 더 즐거울 거예요
And here's why.
이유는 이거예요
The great thing about this problem is that it's very easy to to measure whether we're doing it well
이 문제의 장점은 우리가 잘하고 있는지 아닌지 측정하기가 아주 쉽다는 거예요
If if we predict if we take a product and we know how much it costs, we can put that in and see how
만약 제품을 선택하고 가격을 안다면 그걸 입력해서 제품의 효과를
well the product does.
볼 수 있어요.
See how well our model does in guessing the price of that product.
우리 모델이 그 제품의 가격을 얼마나 잘 추산하는지 보세요
Where are some other text generation problems are harder to to measure in a very human understandable
다른 문서 생성 문제도 있습니다. 인간이 이해할 수 있는 방식으로 측정하기 어려운 문제들이죠.
way.
두 언어 간의 번역을 할 때, 무언가가 영어를 통해 좋은 스페인어를
is generating good Spanish from from English, but how good becomes a judgment call.
생성하는지 알 수 있지만 얼마나 좋은지는 판단할 수 있죠
And there are of course scoring methodologies.
물론 방법론도 채점하고요
But then you get into a lot of complexity about how they work and, and whether you're actually doing
하지만 Get들이 작동하는 방식과 제가 정말 잘하고 있는지에 대한 복잡한 심경이
better or not.
생기죠
So, you know, there are lots of other problems that are more text generation related, such as building
텍스트 생성 관련 문제들이 많습니다 제품 설명을 실제로 적을 수 있는 뭔가를 만드는
something that would actually write the description of a product, but they're not as easy to measure
것처럼요 하지만 가격을 제시하는 것만큼 측정하기가
as just saying, come up with a price.
쉽지는 않죠
Come up with the price is fabulously simple to measure.
가격을 생각해 보면 측정하기가 아주 쉬워요
If we're doing it well and and measure it in a very humanly understandable way.
우리가 잘한다면 인간적으로 이해할 수 있는 방법으로 측정할 수 있어요
Not with some fancy data science metric like perplexity and stuff, but with something that we'll all
복잡한 데이터 측정법 같은 거 말고 모두가 이해할 수 있는
understand.
거요
How accurate is the price of this fridge that we've just told it?
방금 말씀드린 냉장고 가격은 얼마나 정확하죠?
We'll be able to tell that and see it and watch the improvement.
개선된 모습을 볼 수 있을 거예요
So for that reason and the other reasons, I actually think this is a really nice, well-defined challenge
그 이유와 다른 이유 때문에 이건 우리가 도전하기에 아주 좋고 잘 정의된 도전이라고
for us to take on, and we're going to have some success with it so that that is the problem for you.
생각해요 그리고 성공도 좀 할 거예요 그게 당신 문제군요
All right.
좋아요
In the next video, we're going to start talking about data and I will see you there.
다음 비디오에선 데이터에 관해 얘기할 겁니다 거기서 뵙죠